wida.us 2018-08-09

# 

WIDA Consortium – ACCESS for ELLs Privacy Policy
Purpose
The purpose of this privacy policy, adopted December 30, 2016, is to provide transparency to
parents, school districts and the public about the WIDA Consortium’s collection and use of
personally identifiable student information for the annual administration of the English
language proficiency assessment ACCESS for ELLs.
Overview
The University of Wisconsin-Madison’s Wisconsin Center for Education Research (WCER) is the
administrative home of the WIDA Consortium. Each WIDA Consortium member state contracts
through its state educational agency or board with WCER to provide the annual administration
of the ACCESS for ELLs assessment in its state. WCER, under State of Wisconsin purchasing laws,
has procured a subcontractor, Data Recognition Corporation (DRC), to provide the WIDA
Assessment Management System (WIDA AMS), the online assessment management system for
the ACCESS for ELLs assessment.
A student takes the ACCESS for ELLs assessment in accordance with their state and school
district’s policies. State and school district personnel manage all students taking the ACCESS for
ELLs through the WIDA AMS.
This policy covers both WIDA’s and DRC’s collection and use of student ACCESS for ELLs
information. Collection and use of a student’s information by state educational agency and
school district personnel are governed by their respective policies and are not covered under
this policy. You should direct any questions about your state and school district’s collection and
use of student information to those agencies’ personnel.
Purpose for us Collecting and Using Student Information
WIDA and DRC collect personally identifiable student information solely for the purpose of
administering the ACCESS for ELLs English language proficiency assessment and assisting state
educational agencies and school districts with their compliance with federal law, currently
enacted as the Every Student Succeeds Act of 2015 (ESSA). ESSA, among other things,
establishes federally supported education programs and activities related to English language
instruction, acquisition and achievement. It requires local educational agencies and institutions
to evaluate and report the biennial progress made by English learners. It also requires state
educational agencies to develop accountability models for English learners that relate to these
children’s development and attainment of English proficiency while meeting challenging State
academic content and student academic achievement standards. WIDA reports the information
it collects back to state educational agencies and school districts for them to demonstrate ESSA
compliance.

Information We Collect
We collect information necessary for a state and school district to administer the ACCESS for
ELLs assessment and meet their ESSA requirements. This includes a student’s name and basic
demographic information, including gender, birth date, race/ethnicity and native language. We
collect a student’s school and district information, including state and/or district identification
numbers and grade level. We also collect information about a student’s status in English
language-learning programs and, if applicable, information about a student’s individual
Education plan, disabilities and assessment accommodations. Finally, we collect information
related to a student’s assessment administration and performance.
Some states whether by state law or policy limit or completely restrict the amount of personally
identifiable student information that we collect. In instances where we do not collect personally
identifiable student information, the state will anonymize the assessment administration by
creating a unique student number that it links to the student. WIDA will report assessment
results and compliance information back to the state using the unique student number and the
state will link the information back to the individual student.
WIDA DOES NOT HAVE ACCESS TO, NOR DOES IT COLLECT, ANY OF THE FOLLOWING
INFORMATION: Social security numbers, student addresses, student email addresses, student
and/or parent financial information and student biometric data/biological characteristics, for
example voice prints.
How We Use Personally Identifiable Student Information
We use personally identifiable student information to track a student through the test
administration and score reporting to the student’s school district. We also use personally
identifiable student information to track a student’s assessment performance over time in
order to provide states and school districts the information they need to demonstrate ESSA
compliance.
When a school district test administrator enters a student’s information into the WIDA AMS,
the WIDA AMS creates a unique identifier for that student’s test administration. By assigning a
unique identifier for each student during the test administration and scoring process, WIDA and
DRC limit the exposure of personally identifiable student information throughout the test
administration and scoring process. When score reports are ready to go to school districts, the
records are linked back to the student via the unique identifier. Similarly, the personally
identifiable student information that WIDA maintains for state and school district ESSA
compliance purposes is de-identified before use and is maintained solely for linking a student’s
record from year to year.
Our WIDA Consortium member state contracts and several state and federal student privacy
laws strictly limit our use of personally identifiable student information to the test

administration and ESSA compliance purposes described in this privacy policy. Additionally, we
cannot sell personally identifiable student information under any circumstance or disclose it to
any third parties for any purpose, except for score reporting in accordance with our test
administration services, that is reporting to school districts. We cannot use personally
identifiable student information for targeted advertising to students or any party. Targeted
advertising means selecting and sending advertisements to a student based on information
obtained or inferred over time from the student’s online behavior, use of applications, or
personally identifiable student information.
We cannot use personally identifiable student information to create personal profiles of
students for any purpose, except for test administration and ESSA compliance purposes
described in this privacy policy. Finally, we cannot measure, capture, record, analyze or create a
record of any biological characteristics of the personally identifiable student information that
we collect. In short, our use of collected personally identifiable student information is limited to
the test administration and ESSA compliance purposes described in this privacy policy and any
other use or disclosure is strictly prohibited.
Please direct your questions on this privacy policy or concerning WIDA’s or DRC’s collection and
use of personally identifiable student information please contact Jonathan Gibson, WIDA State
Relations Specialist at (385) 201-9414 or jlgibson@wisc.edu.
